<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[By the Privy Council] [the several rates for  wages for the East Riding]</title>
            <author>Yorkshire (England)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3129</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143010</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33143010</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28188</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21900)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28188)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1874:95)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[By the Privy Council] [the several rates for  wages for the East Riding]</title>
                  <author>Yorkshire (England)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the Deputies of Christopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1593. Iuly 30.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: first page lacking. Title supplied from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wages --  Law and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Yorkshire (England) --  History --  16th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28188:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <head>Eaſtriding in the Countie of Yorke.</head>
            <p>A Certificate of the rate and appointment of the ſeuerall wages for artificers, handicraftſmen, huſbandmen, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, ſeruants, workemen and apprentices of huſbandry, within the Eaſtriding of the Countie of Yorke, made and agreed vpon by Iohn Hotham, Marmaduke Grimſtone, Robert Conſtable, Iohn Gaite, Iohn Alrede, Launcelot Alford, and Iohn Readman Eſquires, Iuſtices of peace within the Eaſtriding of the ſaid Countie, at the generall Seſſions of peace holden before vs at Dripoole, within the ſaid Countie, the xxvi. day of April, in the xxxv. yere of the raigne of our moſt gracious Soueraigne Lady Elizabeth, by the grace of God Queene of England, France and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. according to the tenor and forme of the act of Parliament in ſuch caſe lately proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as followeth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Seruants and Artificers of husbandry.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ayliffe of huſbandry, that in theſe parts is called an ouerman, that is hired with a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or rich yeoman that doeth not labour himſelfe, but putteth his whole charge to his ſeruants, ſhall not take by the yeere for his wages with meat &amp; drinke, about xxxiii. s. iiii. d. and a liuery, or vi. s. viii. d. for the ſame.</p>
               <p>A chiefe ſeruant of a huſbandman that ouerſeeth his ſeruants, and the chiefe ſheepeheard or feoman of or to a gentleman, ſhall not take for his wages with meate and drinke, aboue xxvi. s. viii. d. and a liuery, or vi. s. viii. d. for the ſame.</p>
               <p>A Milner that is ſkilfull in mending of hir Mill, ſhal haue by yere xxvi. s. viii. d and a liuery, or vi. s. viii. d. for the ſame.</p>
               <p>A ſeruant in huſbandry that can mowe or plough well, ſhall not take for his wages by yeere with meat and drink, aboue xxiii. s. iiii. d. and a liuery, or vi. s. viii. d. for the ſame. And euery other common ſeruant in huſbandry, ſhall not take by yeere aboue xx. s. and v. s. for a liuery.</p>
               <p>A yong man betweene the age of xii. and xviii. yeeres, ſhall not take by the yeere with meat and drinke, aboue xvi. s. and no liuery.</p>
               <p>A woman ſeruant that taketh charge of brewing, baking, kitching, milkehouſe or malting, that is hired with a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman or rich yeoman, whoſe wife doeth not take the paines and charge vpon her, ſhall not take wages by yeere, with meate and drinke, aboue xvi. s. liuery, iiii. s.</p>
               <p>A woman ſeruant that ſerueth an huſbandman or feeman, or any other woman ſeruant ſhall not take by the yeere with meat and drinke, aboue xiii. s. iiii. d and a liuery, or iii. s. iiii. d. for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Harueſt worke.</head>
               <p>A mower of graſſe or corne ſhall not take by the day with meat and drinke, aboue iiii. d. without meat and drinke, x. d.</p>
               <p>A ſhearer or bindeer of corne ſhall not take by the day with meat and drinke, aboue ii. d. without meat and drinke, v. d.</p>
               <p>No man ſhall take for the mowing of an acre of med<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w, without meat and drinke, aboue x. d. and for mowing of an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre of corne without meat and drinke, viii. d.</p>
               <p>A haymaker, weeder, or looker of corne, ſhall not take by the day with meate and drinke, aboue i. d. without meate and drinke, not aboue iiii. d.</p>
               <p>A maſter Tailer that ſhall make gentlemen or gentlewomen their apparell ſhall not take by the day aboue iiii. d. and other common tailers, not aboue ii. d. with meat and drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Labourers of husbandry.</head>
               <p>Euery common labourer for ditching, paling, railing, hedging, threſhing, &amp; other common labourers, from the feaſt of all Saints, to the firſt of March, ſhal not take for wages by the day with meat and drinke, aboue i. d. ob. and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meat and orinke, not aboue iiii. d. and from the firſt of March vntill the feaſt of all Saints, not aboue ii. d. by the day with meate and drinke, and without meat and drinke, not aboue. v. d.</p>
               <p>Threſhing of a quarter of hard corne, not aboue viii. d. for a quarter of peaſe or beanes, not aboue v. d. for a quarter of barley, not aboue iiii. d. a quarter of Oates, not aboue iii. d. ob. without meat and drinke.</p>
               <p>No man ſhall take for caſting or ſetting of any ditch, hauing the quicke wood ready layde beſide him which ditch is no more then one yard and three quarters of a yard broad, and an elle deepe, aboue iii. d. for euery rodde, and when the ditch is bigger or leſſer, more or leſſe, according to the quantitie and rate.</p>
               <p>No man that ſcoureth two good graftes with a ſpade in a ditch ſhall take for one rodde ſcouring aboue i. ob. and if hee take there grafts, ii. d. and not aboue.</p>
               <p>No man ſhall take for making of a rough dry ſtone wall, hauing the ſtone laid by him, which wall is one yard and a halfe high, and halfe a yard thicke, aboue xii. d. a rodde, without meat and drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Artificers and handicraftsmen.</head>
               <p>A maſter Maſon that taketh the charge of a mans building, hauing vnder him or them, one, two, or three men, that haue bene two or three yeeres at the occupation, ſhall not take for wages for himſelfe by the day at any time of the yeere, with meate and drinke, aboue vi. d. and without meate and drinke, not aboue x. d. and for euery one that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vnder him, he ſhall not take by the day with meat and drinke from the feaſt of Saint Michael the Archangell to the xxv. day of March, not aboue iii. d. and without meat &amp; drink, not aboue viii. d and from the xxv. of March vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſt of S. Michael the archangel, with meat &amp; drink, not aboue iiii. d. &amp; without meat &amp; drink, not aboue viii. d.</p>
               <p>A maſter carpenter who taketh charge of building, that hath one, two or three men vnder him that haue beene two yeeres at the ſcience ſhal not take for wages by the day without meat and drinke, not aboue x. d. and with meate and drinke, aboue iiii. d.</p>
               <p>A Maſon or other carpenter that hath but one man or none, and that are not maſter of a charge or of a building, but of other worke, a shewing, ſquaring, w<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lling, or ſuch like, or plumber, glaſier, limeburner, couper, brickm<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ker, that<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, turners, bricklayers, ſcl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters, <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd tylers, ſhal not take by the day for wages with meate and drinke from the the Annunciation of our Lady vntil Michaelmas aboue iiii. d. and without meat and drinke, aboue viii. d. and from the feaſt of Saint Michael the Archangell vntil the feaſt of the Annunciation of our Lady, with meat and drinke, not aboue iii. d. and without meat and drinke, not aboue vii. d. except Thatchers, who may take iiii. d. by the day throughout the whole yee<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e with meate and drinke.</p>
               <p>A ſhipcarpenter ſhall not take for his wages by the day from the Annunciation of our Lady, vntill the feaſt of Saint Michael with meate and drinke, aboue vi. d. and without meat and drinke, not aboue x. d. &amp; from the feaſt of S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>int Michael vntill the Lady day in Lent, not aboue iiii. d. with meate and drinke, and without, not aboue viii. d.</p>
               <p>A clincher ſhal not take for his wages by the day, from the Lady day in Lent vntill Michaelm<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s with meat &amp; drinke, not aboue iiii. d. and without, not aboue vi. d. and from the feaſt of Saint Michael the Archangel vntill the Annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation of our Lady not aboue iii. d. by the day with meate and drinke, and without, not aboue vii. d.</p>
               <p>I holder ſhal not take for his wages by the day from the Annunciation of our Lady, vntil the feaſt of Saint Michael with meat and drinke, not aboue iii. d. and without, not aboue vi. d. and from the feaſt of Saint Michael, vntill the Annunciation of our Lady, not aboue ii. d. by the day with meat &amp; drinke, and without meat &amp; drink, not aboue. vi. d.</p>
               <p>All which ſaid wages and liueries by vs the ſaid Iuſtices rated in forme aforeſaid, we hauing conſideration to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of all maner of victuall, and other neceſſaries in theſe North parts do thinke indifferent and meete to continue within the Eaſtriding of the ſaid Countie of Yorke, for the yeere next to come.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>1593. Iuly. 30.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <lb/>
God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by the Deputies of CHRISTOPHER BARKER, <hi>Printer of the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
